[boy] This is Berk.
It's twelve days north of hopeless
and a few degrees south
of freezing to death.
It's located solidly
on the meridian of misery.
My village. In a word, sturdy.
It's been here for seven generations,
but every single building is new.
We have fishing, hunting
and a charming view of the sunsets.
The only problems are the pests.
You see, most places
have mice or mosquitoes.
We have...
...dragons.
[boy] Most people would leave. Not us.
We're Vikings.
We have stubbornness issues.
My name is Hiccup.
Great name, I know.
But it's not the worst.
Parents believe a hideous name
will frighten off gnomes and trolls.
Like our charming Viking
demeanour wouldn't do that.
[roars] Morning!
- What are you doing here?!
- Get inside!
- What are you doing out?!
- Get back inside!
Hiccup! What is he doing...?
What are you doing out?!
Get inside!
[Hiccup] That's Stoick the Vast,
chief of the tribe.
They say when he was a baby, he popped
a dragon's head clean off its shoulders.
Do I believe it?
Yes, I do.
What have we got?
Gronckles. Nadders.
Zipplebacks.
Oh, and Hoark saw
a Monstrous Nightmare.
- Any Night Furies?
- [man] None so far.
- Good.
- [man 2] Hoist the torches!
[grunts]
Oh! Nice of you to join the party!
I thought you'd been carried off!
Who, me? Come on,
I'm way too muscular for their taste.
They wouldn't know
what to do with all this.
They need toothpicks, don't they?
[Hiccup] The meathead with attitude
and interchangeable hands is Gobber.
I've been his apprentice
since I was little.
Well, littler.
Move to the lower defences.
We'll counterattack with the catapults.
See? Old village,
lots and lots of new houses.
- Fire!
- [girl] Let's go!
[Hiccup] That's Fishlegs, Snotlout,
the twins: Ruffnut and Tuffnut...
...and...
...Astrid.
Oh, their job is so much cooler.
- Eh!
- Come on. Let me out, please.
I need to make my mark.
You've made plenty of marks,
all in the wrong places.
Please, two minutes. I'll kill a dragon.
My life will get infinitely better.
I might even get a date.
You can't lift a hammer.
You can't swing an axe.
You can't even throw one of these!
OK, fine, but this will throw it for me.
- Ohh!
- [groans]
See? Now this right here
is what I'm talking about!
- [stammers] Mild calibration issue...
- Hiccup!
If you ever want to get
out there to fight dragons...
...you need to stop all this.
But you just pointed to all of me.
Yes, that's it!
Stop being all of you.
- Ohh...
- Oh, yes.
You, sir, are playing
a dangerous game.
Keeping this much
raw Vikingness contained?
- There will be consequences!
- I'll take my chances.
Sword. Sharpen. Now.
[Hiccup] One day, I'll get out there.
Because killing a dragon...
...is everything around here.
A Nadder head is sure
to get me at least noticed.
Gronckles are tough.
Taking down one of those
would definitely get me a girlfriend.
A Zippleback?
- [spits]
- [people scream]
[Hiccup] Exotic. Two heads,
twice the status.
They found the sheep!
Concentrate fire over the lower bank.
- Fire!
- [grunts]
And then there's
the Monstrous Nightmare.
Only the best Vikings go after those.
They have this nasty habit
of setting themselves on fire.
[snarling]
Reload! I'll take care of this.
But the ultimate prize
is the dragon no one's ever seen.
- We call it the...
- Night Fury!
- Get down!
- [screams]
Jump!
This thing never steals food,
never shows itself, and...
...never misses.
No one has ever killed a Night Fury.
That's why I'm going to be the first.
Man the fort, Hiccup.
They need me out there.
Stay. Put. There.
You know what I mean. [yells]
- [man] Where are you going?
- Yeah, I know!
- [woman] Hiccup!
- Be right back!
[sheep braying]
[man] Let's get 'em!
[Stoick] Mind yourselves!
The devils still have
some juice in them!
[grunts]
[dragon roars in distance]
Come on.
Give me something to shoot at.
- Give me something to shoot at.
- [dragon roars]
[dragon approaching]
[dragon divebombing]
- [weapon fires]
- Aah!
[dragon roars]
I hit it. Yes, I hit it!
- Did anybody see that?
- [growls]
Except for you.
[Hiccup screaming]
- [sighs] Do not let them escape!
- [man] Right!
- [dragon growling]
- [screams]
[panting]
[dragon growls]
[roars]
- [burps]
- You're all out.
[grunting]
[Hiccup] Oh, and there's
one more thing you need to know.
[screams]
- [woman yells]
- [metal torch clanging]
- [glass breaks]
- Sorry, Dad.
[screaming]
- [sheep braying]
- [dragons growling]
OK, but I hit a Night Fury. Aah!
It's not like the last few times, Dad!
I really, actually hit it!
You guys were busy.
I had a very clear shot.
It went down off Raven Point.
Let's get a search party...
Stop! Just stop.
Every time you step outside,
disaster follows.
Can you not see that
I have bigger problems?
Winter is almost here and I have
an entire village to feed!
Between you and me, the village could do
with a little less feeding.
This isn't a joke, Hiccup!
[groans] Why can't you
follow the simplest orders?
I can't stop myself. I see a dragon
and I have to just kill it.
It's who I am, Dad.
Oh, you're many things, Hiccup.
But a dragon killer is not one of them.
Get back to the house.
Make sure he gets there.
I have his mess to clean up.
- [girl laughing]
- Quite the performance.
I've never seen anyone
mess up that badly. That helped.
Thank you, thank you. I was trying.
Ow! [grunts]
- I really did hit one.
- [Gobber] Sure, Hiccup.
- He never listens.
- It runs in the family.
When he does, it's with
this disappointed scowl,
like someone skimped
on meat in his sandwich.
[mimics Stoick]
"Excuse me, barmaid.
I'm afraid you brought me
the wrong offspring.
I ordered an extra-large boy
with beefy arms,
extra guts and glory on the side.
This here, this is a talking fishbone."
You're thinking about this wrong.
It's not so much what you look like,
it's what's inside that he can't stand.
Thank you for summing that up.
Look, the point is, stop trying so hard
to be something you're not.
I just want to be one of you guys.
- [door closes]
- [sighs]
[Stoick] Either we finish them
or they'll finish us!
It's the only way we'll be rid of them.
If we find the nest and destroy it,
the dragons will leave.
They'll find another home!
One more search before the ice sets in.
Those ships never come back.
We're Vikings. It's an occupational
hazard. Now who's with me?!
[man] Count me out.
- Today's no good for me.
- I have to do my axe returns.
All right. Those who stay
will look after Hiccup.
- [woman] To the ships!
- Aye. That's more like it.
Right. I'll pack my undies.
No, I need you to stay
and train some new recruits.
Perfect. And, while I'm busy,
Hiccup can cover the stall.
Molten steel, razor-sharp blades,
lots of time to himself.
What could possibly go wrong?
[groans] What am I going
to do with him, Gobber?
Put him in training.
- No, I'm serious.
- So am I.
He'd be killed before
the first dragon is out of its cage.
- You don't know that.
- I do, actually.
- No, you don't.
- No, I do.
No, you don't.
Listen, you know what he's like.
From the time he could crawl,
he's been... different.
[sighs] He doesn't listen.
He has the attention span of a sparrow.
I take him fishing and
he goes hunting for trolls!
Trolls exist.
They steal your socks.
But only the left ones.
What's with that?
- When I was a boy...
- Here we go.
...my father told me to bang my head
against a rock and I did it.
I thought it was crazy,
but I didn't question him.
- And you know what happened?
- You got a headache.
That rock split in two.
It taught me what
a Viking could do, Gobber.
He could crush mountains,
level forests, tame seas!
Even as a boy, I knew what I was,
what I had to become.
Hiccup is not that boy.
You can't stop him, Stoick.
You can only prepare him.
I know it seems hopeless, but you won't
always be around to protect him.
He's going to get out there again.
He's probably out there now.
[birds singing in distance]
[deep breath]
[exhales]
[sighs] Oh, the gods hate me.
Some people lose their knife
or their mug. Not me.
I manage to lose an entire dragon.
Ow!
[bird calling, faint]
[gasps, pants]
[sighs, gasps]
Oh, wow. I did it.
Ohh, I did it. This...
This fixes everything! Yes!
I have brought down
this mighty beast!
[dragon bellows]
[heavy breathing]
[guttural growl]
[exhales]
[exhales] I'm going to kill you, dragon.
Then I'll cut out your heart
and take it to my father.
I am a Viking. I am a Viking!
[grunts]
[deep breathing]
[moans]
I did this.
[knife saws rope]
- [growling]
- [gasps]
[low growl]
[panting] Uh...
[snarls]
[roaring]
[panting]
- [dragon thumping]
- [growling]
[wailing]
[moans]
[door opens]
- Hiccup.
- Dad, uh...
...I have to talk to you, Dad.
I need to speak with you, too, son.
- I don't want to fight dragons.
- It's time you learn to fight dragons.
- Uh, you go first.
- No, you go first.
All right. [sighs]
You get your wish.
Dragon training...
you start in the morning.
Oh, man, I should have
gone first. Uh...
I was thinking, you know,
we have a surplus
of dragon-fighting Vikings,
but do we have enough bread-making
Vikings or small-home-repair Vikings?
- You'll need this.
- [grunts]
I don't want to fight dragons.
- [chuckles] Come on. Yes, you do.
- Rephrase.
Dad, I can't kill dragons.
But you will kill dragons.
No, I'm really very extra-sure
that I won't.
- It's time, Hiccup.
- Can you not hear me?
This is serious, son.
When you carry this axe,
you carry all of us with you.
Which means you walk like us,
you talk like us...
...you think like us.
No more of... this.
You just gestured to all of me.
- Deal?
- This conversation is very one-sided.
- [sighs] Deal.
Good.
Train hard.
I'll be back. Probably.
And I'll be here.
Maybe.
Welcome to dragon training!
No turning back.
I hope I get some serious burns.
I'm hoping for some mauling,
like on my shoulder or back.
Yeah, it's only fun
if you get a scar out of it.
Yeah, no kidding, right?
Pain. Love it.
Oh, great. Who let him in?
Let's get started!
The recruit who does best
will win the honour of
killing his first dragon
in front of the entire village.
Hiccup already killed a Night Fury,
so does that disqualify him?
Can I transfer to the class
with the cool Vikings?
Don't worry.
You're small and weak...
that'll make you less of a target.
They'll see you as sick or insane
and go after the more Viking-like
teens instead. [laughs]
Behind these doors are just
a few of the many species
you will learn to fight!
- The Deadly Nadder!
- Speed 8, armour 16.
- The Hideous Zippleback.
- Plus 11 stealth. Times 2.
- The Monstrous Nightmare.
- Firepower 15.
- The Terrible Terror.
- Attack 8, venom 12.
Can you stop that?!
And the Gronckle.
- [whispers] Jaw strength 8.
- Whoa! Whoa!
Wait, aren't you gonna teach us first?
I believe in learning on the job.
[snarling]
[Gobber] Today is about survival.
If you get blasted...
...you're dead!
What's the first thing you'll need?
- A doctor?
- Plus 5 speed?
- A shield.
- Shields. Go!
Your most important piece
of equipment is your shield!
If you must choose between a sword
or a shield, take the shield!
- Let go of my shield!
- There are a million shields!
Take that one. It has a flower...
girls like flowers. Aah!
Oops, this one has blood on it.
- [Gobber] Tuffnut, Ruffnut! You're out!
- What?
Shields are good for another thing.
Noise! Make lots of it
to throw off a dragon's aim!
- [growls]
- [Gobber] All dragons have
a limited number of shots.
How many does a Gronckle have?
- Five?
- No, six!
[Gobber] Correct, six!
That's one for each of you!
- Fishlegs, out!
- Aaah!
- Hiccup, get in there!
- [snarls]
- I moved into my parents' basement.
Come by sometime and work out.
- You look like you work out. Aah!
- [Gobber] Snotlout! You're done!
- So it's just you and me, huh?
- Nope, just you.
- [Gobber] One shot left!
- [panting]
Hiccup!
- [gasping]
- [snarls]
And that's six.
Go back to bed, you overgrown sausage!
You'll get another chance,
don't you worry.
Remember, a dragon will always,
always go for the kill.
- [door rattles]
- [dragon growls]
So... why didn't you?
[chirping]
This was stupid.
- [gasps]
- [dragon growls]
[scraping]
[growling]
- [growls]
- [panting]
[growls]
[gasps]
[snarls]
[bellows, growls]
Why don't you just fly away?
[roars]
[growls]
[gasps]
[pencil clatters]
[low growl]
[Gobber] Where did Astrid
go wrong in the ring today?
[Astrid] I mistimed my somersault dive.
It was sloppy.
- It threw off my reverse tumble.
- [Ruffnut] Yeah, we noticed.
No, no, you were great.
That was so "Astrid."
She's right. You have to be
tough on yourselves.
Where did Hiccup go wrong?
- Uh, he showed up.
- He didn't get eaten.
He's never where he should be.
Thank you, Astrid.
You need to live and breathe this stuff.
The dragon manual.
Everything we know about
every dragon we know of.
- [thunder rumbles]
- Ah.
No attacks tonight. Study up.
Wait, you mean read?
While we're still alive?
Why read words when you
can just kill the stuff
the words tell you stuff about?
I've read it seven times.
There's this water dragon
that sprays boiling water at your face.
And there's this other one...
Yeah. That sounds great.
- There was a chance I'd read it...
- But now...
You guys read. I'll go kill stuff.
Another one has spines like trees.
- So I guess we'll share?
- Read it.
Uh, all mine, then. Wow.
So, OK, I'll see you...
- [door slams]
- ...tomorrow.
[thunder rumbles]
Dragon classifications.
Strike class.
Fear class. Mystery class.
- [thunder rumbles]
- Thunderdrum.
This reclusive dragon inhabits sea caves
and dark tide pools.
When startled, the Thunderdrum
produces a concussive sound
that can kill a man at close range.
Extremely dangerous. Kill on sight.
Timberjack. This gigantic creature
has razor-sharp wings
that can slice through full-grown trees.
Extremely dangerous. Kill on sight.
Scauldron. Sprays scalding
water at its victim.
Extremely dangerous.
- [thunderclap]
- [gasps]
Changewing. Even newly hatched dragons
can spray acid. Kill on sight.
Gronckle. Zippleback. The Skrill.
Bone Knapper. Whispering Death.
Burns its victims.
Buries its victims.
Chokes its victims.
Turns its victims inside out.
Extremely dangerous.
Kill on sight.
Kill on sight. Kill on sight.
Night Fury.
Speed unknown.
Size unknown.
The unholy offspring
of lightning and death itself.
Never engage this dragon.
Your only chance:
hide and pray it does not find you.
[Stoick] I can almost smell them.
They're close.
Steady.
Take us in.
Hard to port.
For Helheim's Gate.
[man] Hard to port!
[Stoick] Steady!
[roaring]
Hey, you know,
I just happened to notice
the book had nothing on Night Furies.
Is there another book, or a sequel?
Maybe a Night Fury pamphlet?
- Whoa!
- [Gobber] Focus, Hiccup!
You're not even trying!
- Today it's all about attack!
- [roars]
Nadders are quick
and light on their feet.
Your job is to be quicker and lighter!
I'm really beginning to question
your teaching methods!
Look for its blind spot!
Every dragon has one.
Find it, hide in it and strike!
- [snarls]
- [groans] Ohh!
[Ruffnut] Do you ever bathe?
If you don't like it,
then just get your own blind spot.
- How about I give you one?
- [Nadder growls]
Blind spot, yes.
Deaf spot, not so much.
[chuckles]
How would one
sneak up on a Night Fury?
No one's ever met one and lived
to tell the tale. Get in there!
- I know, I know, but hypothetically...
- [Astrid] Hiccup!
Get down.
[growling]
[growls]
[roars]
Watch out, babe.
I'll take care of this.
- The sun was in my eyes, Astrid.
- [Nadder roars]
What do you want me to do,
block the sun?
I could do that
but I don't have time!
[Hiccup] They probably...
...take the daytime off,
right? Like a cat.
- Has anyone ever seen one napping?
- Hiccup!
Hiccup!
Ooh! Love on the battlefield.
- [Ruffnut] She could do better.
- Let me... Why don't you...? Aaah!
Ow! Ow! Ow!
- [panting]
- [Gobber] Well done, Astrid.
Is this some kind of a joke to you?
Our parents' war
is about to become ours.
Figure out which side you're on.
[gasps]
[sniffs, growls]
[growls]
[snarls]
[splash]
[low growl]
[chuckles] Toothless.
I could have sworn you had...
[gasps]
...teeth.
Uh... [stammers]
No, no, no.
I... I don't have any more!
Ugh!
[sighs]
Uh...
- Mmm!
- [low growl]
Mm-hmm.
- [swallows]
- [moans]
[swallows, retches]
[gulps, shudders]
[slurps, smacks lips]
[sighs]
[guttural grunts]
[snarls]
[roars]
[chirping]
[low growl]
[purring growl]
[tree branch snapping]
[growls, snarls]
[guttural growl]
[snarls]
[purrs]
[snarls, purrs]
[snarling, purring]
[dragon exhales]
[snarls]
[Gobber] And with one twist,
he took my hand and swallowed it whole!
I saw the look on his face...
I was delicious.
He must have passed the word,
because it wasn't a month
before another one of them took my leg.
Isn't it weird to think
your hand was inside a dragon?
Like if your mind was still
in control of it,
you could have killed the dragon
from inside by crushing his heart.
I swear, I'm so angry. I'll avenge your
beautiful hand and your beautiful foot.
I'll chop off the legs of every dragon
I fight, with my face.
Mm-mmm, no. It's the wings
and tail you really want.
If it can't fly, it can't get away.
A downed dragon is a dead dragon.
[yawns]
All right, I'm off to bed.
You should be, too.
Tomorrow we get to the big boys,
slowly but surely
making our way up
to the Monstrous Nightmare.
But who'll win the honour of killing it?
It's gonna be me.
It's my destiny. See?
[gasps] Your mom let you get a tattoo?
[Tuffnut] It's not a tattoo,
it's a birthmark.
[Ruffnut] OK, I've been stuck
with you since birth,
and that was never there before.
[Tuffnut] Yes, it was. You've just
never seen me from the left side.
[sizzles]
[Hiccup] Hey, Toothless.
I brought breakfast. I hope...
I hope you're hungry.
OK, that's disgusting.
We've got some salmon,
some nice Icelandic cod...
...and a whole smoked eel.
[snarls]
- [roars]
- No, no, no, no, no! It's OK.
Yeah, I don't really
like eel much, either.
OK, that's it.
That's it. Just stick
with the good stuff.
And don't you mind me.
I'll just be back here,
minding my own business.
- [grunts]
- [Toothless growls]
[gasps] It's OK.
[grunting]
OK.
[guttural growl]
That's not too bad. It works.
Whoa! Whooaa!
No, no, no, no!
Whoa!
Oh, my...! It's working!
Yes, yes! I did it!
Aaah!
[shrieks]
- [Hiccup] Yeah!
- [Gobber] Today is about teamwork.
Now, a wet dragon head
can't light its fire.
The Hideous Zippleback
is extra tricky.
One head breathes gas,
the other head lights it.
Your job is to know which is which.
Razor-sharp serrated teeth
that inject venom for pre-digestion.
Prefers ambush attack,
crushing its victims...
Will you please stop that?!
[dragon, gurgling]
If that dragon shows either
of his faces, I'm gonna...
There!
Hey, it's us, idiots!
Your butts are getting bigger.
We thought you were a dragon.
Not that there's anything wrong
with a dragonesque figure... Ow!
- [shouting]
- Wait.
- [Tuffnut yelling]
- [dragon shrieks]
Oh, I'm hurt!
I am very much hurt!
Chances of survival are
dwindling to single digits now.
[gurgles, sniffs]
Whoa, whoa! [stammering]
Oh. Heh! Wrong head.
- Fishlegs!
- [screaming]
- [gurgles, sparking]
- [Gobber] Now, Hiccup!
Oh, come on.
[snarling, roars]
- Hiccup!
- [dragon shrieks]
Back, back, back!
Now, don't you make me
tell you again! Yes, that's right.
Back into your cage.
Now think about what you've done.
[growling, muffled]
OK, so are we done?
'Cause I've got some things I need to...
Yep, I'll see you tomorrow!
- [growls]
- Hey!
[growls]
- [roars]
- [grunts]
[Toothless purrs]
- [dragon snarls]
- [Snotlout] Whoa!
[sniffing]
I've never seen a Gronckle do that.
I left my axe back in the ring.
You guys go on ahead.
I'll catch up with you.
[guttural growls]
[gurgle]
- Hyah!
- [roars]
[Astrid yells]
[clamouring]
[Gobber] Meet the Terrible Terror.
[scoffs] It's like the size of my...
- [crowd groans]
- [Tuffnut] Get it off! [groans]
Oh, I'm hurt! I am very much hurt!
- [grunts]
- Wow! He's better than you ever were.
[grunting]
[groans]
[purrs, growls]
[Hiccup] Oh, great.
Hiccup.
[metal clatters]
[Astrid] Hiccup? Are you in there?
Astrid. Hey.
Hi, Astrid. Hi, Astrid. Hi, Astrid.
I normally don't care what people do,
but you're acting weird.
- Ohh! [nervous chuckle]
- Well, weirder.
- [sea birds cawing]
- [Vikings moaning]
I trust you found the nest, at least?
Not even close.
Oh. Excellent.
I hope you had more success than me.
If by success, you mean
your parenting troubles are over, yes.
Congratulations, Stoick!
Everyone is so relieved!
Out with the old
and in with the new, right?
- No one will miss that nuisance!
- We're throwing a party to celebrate!
- Come over here.
- Hurry!
He's gone?
Yeah. Most afternoons,
but who can blame him?
The life of a celebrity
is very rough.
He can barely walk through the village
without being swarmed by his new fans.
- Hiccup?
- Who would have thought it, eh?
He has this way with the beasts.
OK, bud. We're gonna
take this nice and slow.
Here we go. Here we go.
Position...
...three... no, four.
All right, it's go time.
It's go time.
[Toothless growls]
Come on, buddy! Come on, buddy!
Yes, it worked!
- [growls]
- Sorry!
- It was my fault.
Yeah, I'm on it.
Position four. Uh, three.
Yeah! Go, baby!
Yes!
Oh, this is amazing!
The wind in my... cheat sheet!
Stop!
- No!
- [roars]
Oh, gosh! Oh, gods! Oh, no!
All right, OK, you've gotta
kind of angle yourself.
OK, no, no, no. Come back down
towards me! Come back down... Ow!
[roars]
[shrieks]
Yeah!
Oh, come on.
[Toothless chomping]
Uh... No, thanks. I'm good.
[dragons shriek]
[snarling]
- [snaps]
- [both growling]
[snarling]
[huffing bellow]
[growling]
[squeaks]
Huh. Not so fireproof
on the inside, are you?
Here you go.
[purring]
Everything we know
about you guys is wrong.
[footsteps approach]
Dad! You're back!
- Uh, Gobber's not here so...
- [Stoick] I know.
I came looking for you.
You did?
You've been keeping secrets.
[stammers] I have?
Just how long did you think
you could hide it?
I... I...
I don't know what you're...
Nothing happens on this island
without me hearing about it.
- Oh?
- So...
...let's talk...
...about that dragon.
Oh, gods.
Dad, I'm so sorry.
I... I was going to tell you.
- I just didn't know how to...
- [chuckling]
- [laughing]
- [nervous laughter]
You're... You're not upset?
What?! I was hoping for this!
Uh... You were?
And believe me,
it only gets better!
Wait till you spill
a Nadder's guts the first time!
And mount your first
Gronckle head on a spear!
What a feeling!
You really had me going there, son!
All those years of the worst Viking
Berk has ever seen.
Odin, it was rough.
I almost gave up on you.
And all the while
you were holding out on me!
Oh, Thor Almighty! [sighs]
With you doing so well in the ring...
...we finally have
something to talk about.
Oh.
Here, I, uh, I brought you something,
to keep you safe in the ring.
Wow. Thanks.
Your mother would have
wanted you to have it.
- It's half of her breastplate.
- [nervous chuckle]
Matching set.
It keeps her close, you know.
Wear it proudly. You deserve it.
You've held up your end of the deal.
[yawns] I should really get to bed.
Yes, good. OK, good talk.
I'll see you back at the house.
Thanks for stopping by...
- ...and for the breast hat.
- I hope you like the hat.
[clears throat]
Well, uh... Yep. Good night.
- [sighs]
- [exhales]
[cheering]
Stay out of my way!
I'm winning this thing.
Please, by all means.
[dragon growls]
This time, this time for sure!
[screams]
- [snoring]
- [crowd cheering]
No! No, son of a half-troll,
- rat-eating, munge-bucket!
- Wait! Wait.
- So, later.
- Oh! Not so fast.
- I'm kind of late for...
- What?!
Late for what, exactly?
Quiet down! The elder has decided.
[crowd gasps, murmurs]
[crowd cheering]
You've done it, Hiccup!
You get to kill the dragon!
- [cheering]
- Yeah!
That's my boy!
Yeah. Yes. I can't wait. I am so...
...leaving! We're leaving.
Let's pack up.
Looks like you and me are
taking a little vacation.
Forever.
[sighs] Oh, man.
[gasps] What the...?!
[stammers] What are you doing here?
I want to know what's going on.
No one just gets as good as you do.
Especially you.
Start talking!
Are you training with someone?
- Training? [stammers]
- It better not involve this.
I know this looks really bad,
but you see...
- [twig snaps]
- This is, uh... Aaah!
You're right. You're right.
You're right.
I'm through with the lies.
I've been making outfits.
So you got me.
It's time everyone knew.
Drag me back, go ahead.
Here we go... Ow!
Why would you do that?!
That's for the lies.
And that's for everything else.
- [Toothless roars]
- [Hiccup] Oh, man.
[gasps] Get down!
- [roars]
- Run, run!
No! It's OK! It's OK.
She's a friend.
You just scared him.
- I scared him?!
- [Toothless growls]
- Who is "him?"
- Uh...
Astrid, Toothless.
Toothless, Astrid.
[snarls]
[mimics fanfare] We're dead.
Whoa, whoa, whoa!
Where do you think you're going?
[panting]
Oh, great Odin's ghost!
Oh, this is it!
[panting]
Hiccup, get me down from here!
You have to give me a chance to explain.
I am not listening
to anything you have to say!
Then I won't speak.
Just let me show you.
Please, Astrid.
- [grunts]
- [branches creak]
[growls]
Now get me down.
Toothless, down. Gently.
See? Nothing to be afraid of.
Whaaah!
Toothless!
What is wrong with you?! Bad dragon!
[nervous laugh] He's not
usually like this.
- Oh, no.
- [screaming]
Toothless, what are you doing?
We need her to like us!
- And now the spinning.
- [Astrid screaming]
Thank you for nothing,
you useless reptile.
OK, I am sorry! I'm sorry.
Just get me off this thing.
All right, I admit it.
This is pretty cool.
It's amazing.
He's amazing.
So what now?
Hiccup, your final exam is tomorrow.
You know you'll have to kill...
- [dragon growls, faint]
- ...kill a dragon.
- Don't remind me.
- [both scream]
[Hiccup] Toothless, what's happening?
- Whoa! What is it?
- [dragons roaring]
Get down!
[roaring]
- What's going on?
- I don't know.
Toothless, you got to
get us out of here, bud.
[snarls]
[Hiccup] It looks like
they're hauling in their kill.
Uh... what does that make us?
[dragons snarling, roaring]
What my dad wouldn't give to find this.
It's satisfying to know all our food
has been dumped down a hole.
- [dragon shrieks]
- They're not eating any of it.
[shudders]
[growling]
- [gasps]
- What is that?
[roars]
All right, bud, we got
to get out of here... now!
[Astrid] No, it totally makes sense.
It's like a giant beehive.
They're the workers
and that's their queen.
It controls them.
Let's find your dad.
No! No.
No, not yet.
They'll kill Toothless.
We have to think this
through carefully.
Hiccup, we just discovered
the dragons' nest,
the thing we've been after
since Vikings first sailed here,
and you want to keep it a secret?
To protect your pet dragon?
Are you serious?
Yes.
OK. Then what do we do?
Just give me until tomorrow.
I'll figure something out.
OK.
That's for kidnapping me.
[growls]
That's for everything else.
What are you looking at?
[crowd] Hiccup! Hiccup!
Hiccup! Hiccup!
Well, I can show my face
in public again! [laughs]
If someone had told me
that in a few short weeks
Hiccup would go from, well,
being, uh, Hiccup
to placing first in dragon training,
I'd have tied him to a mast and
shipped him off for fear he'd gone mad!
- [cheering]
- And you know it! [laughs]
But here we are.
And no one is more surprised
or more proud than I am.
Today, my boy becomes a Viking.
- Today, he becomes one of us!
- [crowd cheers]
Be careful with that dragon.
It's not the dragon
I'm worried about.
- [Astrid] What are you going to do?
- Put an end to this. I have to try.
Astrid, if something goes wrong,
just make sure they
don't find Toothless.
I will. Just promise me
it won't go wrong.
It's time, Hiccup.
Knock 'em dead.
[crowd chanting, applause]
Yeah! Show 'em how it's done.
Hiccup! Hiccup!
Hmm, I'd have gone for the hammer.
[deep breath, exhales]
I'm ready.
- [shrieking]
- [crowd gasps]
[growling]
[man] Go on, Hiccup. Give it to him!
What is he doing?
[murmuring]
Hey, it's OK. It's OK.
I'm not one of them.
- [gasps]
- What's he thinking?
- Stop the fight.
- [Hiccup] No!
I need you all to see this.
They're not what we think they are.
We don't have to kill them.
I said, stop the fight!
- [crowd gasps]
- Aaah!
Out of my way!
Hiccup!
[growling]
Aaah!
Hiccup!
[growls]
This way!
- [snarling]
- [Toothless divebombs]
[shrieks]
[clamouring]
Night Fury!
[roars]
All right, Toothless, go.
Get out of here.
- Go, go!
- [Astrid] Stoick, no!
- Dad, he won't hurt you!
- [growls]
No, don't! You're only making it worse!
Toothless, stop!
No! No!
- [moans]
- [panting]
[man] Get him!
No, no! Please don't hurt him!
Please don't hurt him.
[grunting]
Put it with the others.
I should have known.
I should have seen the signs.
- Dad?
- We had a deal!
I know we did. That was before...
Aw, it's all so messed up.
So everything in the ring, a trick?
A lie?
I screwed up. I should have
told you before now. I just...
Take this out on me, be mad at me,
but please, just don't hurt Toothless.
The dragon? That's what
you're worried about?
Not the people you almost killed?
He was protecting me!
He's not dangerous.
They've killed hundreds of us!
And we've killed thousands of them!
They defend themselves, that's all!
They raid us because they have to.
If they don't bring enough food back,
they're eaten themselves.
There's something else on their island.
It's a dragon like...
Their island?
So you've been to the nest?
- Did I say nest?
- How did you find it?
What? No, I didn't. Toothless did.
Only a dragon can find the island.
No, no, no. No, Dad. No, please,
it's not what you think.
You don't know what you're up against.
It's like nothing you've ever seen.
Dad, please. I promise you,
you can't win this one!
No, Dad. No.
For once in your life,
would you please just listen to me?!
You've thrown your lot in with them.
You're not a Viking.
You're not my son.
Ready the ships!
[man] This way.
[growls]
[Toothless growling]
[roaring]
Set sail!
We head for Helheim's Gate.
Lead us home, devil.
It's a mess.
You must feel horrible.
You've lost everything:
your father, your tribe,
your best friend.
Thank you for summing that up.
Why couldn't I have killed that dragon
when I found him in the woods?
Would have been better for everyone.
Yep. The rest of us would've done it.
So why didn't you?
Why didn't you?
I don't know.
- I couldn't.
- That's not an answer.
Why is this so important to you
all of a sudden?
Because I want to remember
what you say right now.
Oh, for the love of...
I was a coward.
I was weak. I wouldn't kill a dragon.
- You said "wouldn't" that time.
- Whatever! I wouldn't!
Three hundred years, and I'm the first
Viking who wouldn't kill a dragon.
First to ride one, though.
So...?
I wouldn't kill him because
he looked as frightened as I was.
I looked at him and I saw myself.
I bet he's really frightened now.
What are you going to do about it?
Eh, probably something stupid.
Good, but you've already done that.
Then something crazy.
That's more like it.
[Stoick] Sound your positions.
Stay within earshot.
- [man] Here!
- [man 2] One length to your stern.
Stoick, I was overhearing some of the
men just now, and, well, some of them
are wondering what it is
we're up to here. Not me, of course.
I know you're always the man
with the plan. But some, not me,
are wondering if there is,
in fact, a plan at all
and what it might be.
Find the nest and take it.
Oh, of course.
Send them running.
The old Viking fallback.
Nice and simple.
- [gurgling]
- Shh, shh!
[gurgling]
Step aside.
Bear to port.
If you're planning on getting eaten,
I'd definitely go with the Gronckle.
You were wise to seek help
from the world's most deadly weapon.
- Uh...
- It's me.
- I love this plan.
- I didn't...
You're crazy. [whispers] I like that.
So, what is the plan?
- That's not really encouraging.
- Oh.
[chuckles] I was wondering
where that went.
[chains rattle]
[sniffing]
- [clamour]
- Stay low and ready your weapons.
[growls, roars]
[animal noises, distant]
We're here.
[animal noises stop]
[exhales]
- [gasps]
- Oh...
Uh-uh.
- Wait! What are you...?
- Shh! Relax.
It's OK. It's OK.
[guttural purr]
Where are you going?
You're gonna need something
to help you hold on.
When we crack this mountain open,
all hell is going to break loose.
In my undies.
Good thing I brought extras.
No matter how this ends, it ends today.
- [rumbling]
- [stone cracking]
[Vikings cheering, distant]
[dragons shrieking, growling]
- [screams]
- [dragons roaring]
[whimpering growl]
Is that it?
- [Gobber] We've done it!
- [cheering]
[dragon roaring, muted]
This isn't over!
Form your ranks! Hold together!
- [rumbling]
- [cracking]
[dragon roaring]
[dragon snarling]
- Get clear!
- [gasps]
- [growling]
- [Vikings yelling]
Beard of Thor! What is that?!
Odin help us.
[roaring]
- Catapults!
- [man] Fire!
- Get to the ships!
- No! No!
[Vikings screaming]
[roars]
- Smart, that one.
- I was a fool.
Lead the men to the far side
of the island!
- Right!
- Gobber, go with the men!
I think I'll stay, in case you're
thinking of doing something crazy.
I can buy them a few minutes
if I give that thing someone to hunt!
Then I can double that time.
- Here!
- Oh, no! Here!
- [snarling]
- Come on! Fight me!
- No, me!
- [growls]
- [dragons roaring]
- [roars]
Ruff, Tuff! Watch your backs!
Move, Fishlegs!
[Tuffnut] Look at us! We're on a dragon.
We're on dragons! All of us!
[Hiccup] Up! Let's move it!
Every bit the boar-headed
stubborn Viking you ever were!
- Fishlegs, break it down!
- OK.
Heavily armoured skull and tail
made for bashing and crushing!
Steer clear of both.
Small eyes, large nostrils!
- Relies on hearing and smell!
- OK, Lout, Legs!
Hang in its blind spot,
keep it confused!
Ruff, Tuff, find out if it has
a shot limit! Make it mad!
- That's my specialty!
- Since when?!
Everyone knows
I'm more irritating! See?
Just do what I told you!
I'll be back as soon as I can!
Don't worry!
We got it covered!
- [Fishlegs] Yeah!
- [Ruffnut] Whoo!
- Troll! Bride of Grendel!
- Butt elf!
[Ruffnut laughs]
Um, this thing
doesn't have a blind spot!
[Toothless roaring]
There!
Go help the others!
OK, hold on. Hold on.
- It's working!
- Yeah, it's working!
[dragons snarling]
Whoa!
I've lost power on the Gronckle!
Snotlout, do something!
- I'm OK!
- [Gronckle groans]
[muffled] Less OK!
I can't miss! What's wrong, buddy?
Something in your eye?
- [roaring]
- [Fishlegs screaming]
Yeah! You're the Viking!
Aaah!
Hey! Whoa!
[roars]
[roaring]
[gasps]
[coughs] Dad?
You got it, bud.
[growls]
[Stoick] Hiccup!
I'm sorry... for everything.
Yeah. Me, too.
You don't have to go up there.
We're Vikings.
It's an occupational hazard.
[dragon snarling]
I'm proud to call you my son.
Thanks, Dad.
- [Toothless roars]
- He's up!
Get Snotlout out of there.
- I'm on it!
- I'm on it first!
Hey, let me drive!
- Don't push me!
- I'll take your teeth out!
[Snotlout] I can't believe that worked!
[sucking in air]
[divebombing]
- Night Fury!
- [gasping]
Get down!
[screaming]
Did you get her?
[playful growl]
Go.
That thing has wings.
OK, let's see if it can use them!
[roaring]
You think that did it?
Well, he can fly.
- [cheering]
- [man] Whoo!
- Go!
- Yeah!
OK, Toothless, time to disappear.
Come on, bud!
- [shrieks]
- Here it comes!
[snarling]
[growling]
- Ooh!
- [gasps]
[roars]
Watch out!
OK, time's up!
Let's see if this works.
[Toothless roars]
Come on! Is that the best you can do?!
[dragon roaring]
Stay with me, buddy.
We're good. Just a bit longer.
- Hold, Toothless.
- [shrieking]
Now!
[dragon growling]
[roaring]
No.
- No! Uhh!
- [growls]
[Stoick coughing]
Hiccup!
Son!
[gasping] Hiccup.
[panting]
[moans]
Oh, son.
I did this.
[gasps]
[growls]
Oh, son, I'm so sorry.
Hiccup!
[gasps] He's alive.
You brought him back alive.
[Vikings laugh and cheer]
- Ooh!
- [growls and roars]
Thank you for saving my son.
Well, you know... most of him.
[soft growl]
[growls]
[guttural growl]
Hey, Toothless.
I'm happy to see you, too, buddy.
[groans] What? Uh...
I'm in my house.
- [slurps]
- Uh, you're in my house.
Does my dad know you're here? Uh...
What? Oh, OK, OK.
Toothless, no.
No, Toothless.
Toothless! Oh, come on.
[sniffs]
[deep breaths, exhales]
[groans]
- Aah!
- [growls]
OK. Thanks, bud.
- [roaring]
- Aaah!
Toothless, stay here.
[Snotlout] Come on, guys.
Get ready!
Hold on tight! Here we go!
What?
[Vikings murmuring, faint]
- I knew it. I'm dead.
- [laughs]
No, but you gave it your best shot.
So, what do you think?
[man] Hey, look, it's Hiccup!
[woman] It's Hiccup!
Turns out all we needed
was a little more of this.
You just gestured to all of me.
Well, most of you.
That bit's my handiwork.
With a little Hiccup flair
thrown in. You think it'll do?
- I might make a few tweaks.
- [laughter]
- Aah!
- That's for scaring me.
What, is it always going
to be this way? 'Cause...
...I could get used to it.
- Welcome home.
- [door opens]
- [man] Night Fury!
- Get down!
- You ready?
- [growls]
[Hiccup] This is Berk.
It snows nine months of the year
and hails the other three.
Any food that grows here
is tough and tasteless.
The people that grow here
are even more so.
- [dragons growling]
- Yeah!
[Hiccup] The only upsides are the pets.
While other places
have ponies or parrots...
...we have...
...dragons.
[Toothless roaring]
[♪ Jonsi: Sticks and Stones]